Ziyang Liu

+1 (437) 577-8388 | email@ziyang.ca | Toronto, ON

Summary

Professional software engineer with 7 years of experience building software and systems around data, and 1 year experience managing engineering teams. Experienced with building data systems from scratch and scaling components to be robust, efficient and performant alongside fast-growing teams.

Experience

CPPIB | Toronto, ON

Senior Data Engineer | 07/2023

Design and build business critical data services and pipelines to enable portfolio managers and analysts to work with large and distributed dataset, eventually unlocking critical business insights through cloud computing

Chan Zuckerberg Initiative | Redwood City, CA Staff Software Engineer | 03/2022 - 06/2023

Led a team of ten software engineers developing a cutting-edge scientific visualization tool in collaboration with scientific open source community

Coordinated effort with cross functional partners in product, design and user research.

Mentored junior engineers and interns.

Chan Zuckerberg Initiative | Redwood City, CA Senior Software Engineer | 09/2020 - 02/2022

Architected robust backend APIs for napari-hub.org.

Led team process building, overseeing the development of best practices around operations and monitoring.

Managed AWS infrastructure and enforcing Infrastructure as Code (IaC) for napari hub frontend and backend.

Facilitated efficient coordination and communication within the team as part-time team scrum master, while also taking on a full-time on-call role to address critical issues ensuring high SLO.

Chan Zuckerberg Initiative | Redwood City, CA Software Engineer | 11/2016 - 08/2020

Designed and implemented robust data pipelines for ingestion and distributed processing of biomedical research data. Worked closely with data scientists to build and optimize machine learning models for production use.

Built CI/CD pipelines to ensure ongoing accuracy and efficiency for our pipeline to handle billions of entries with Github Actions.

Skills

Data Engineering, Python, Java, Docker/Kubernetes, Airflow, CI/CD, Operation/Monitoring, Spark, AWS, SQL/NoSQL Databases, Rest API

Education

University of Waterloo | Waterloo, ON Computer Science | 08/2016